I've always written primarily about architecture,
كنت دائما أكتب بالأساس عن المعمار،
about buildings, and writing about architecture
عن البنايات، والكتابة عن المعمار
is based on certain assumptions.
مبنية على الافتراضات.
An architect designs a building, and it becomes a place,
يصمم المعماري بناية فتصبح مكانا،
or many architects design many buildings, and it becomes
أو يصمم المعماريون بنايات عديدة،
a city, and regardless of this complicated mix of forces
فتتكون مدينة، وبغض النظر عن هذا المزيج من عوامل
of politics and culture and economics that shapes
السياسة والثقافة والاقتصاد التي تحدد معالم
these places, at the end of the day, you can go
هذه الأماكن، في نهاية الأمر، يمكنك الذهاب
and you can visit them. You can walk around them.
ويمكنك زيارتها. وأن تتنزه حولها.
You can smell them. You can get a feel for them.
يمكن أن تشتم رائحتها، يمكن أن تحس بها.
You can experience their sense of place.
يمكن أن تتحسس معنى المكان.
But what was striking to me over the last several years
لكن ما كان يزعجني خلال السنوات العديدة الماضية
was that less and less was I going out into the world,
هو أنه كلما ابتعدت أكثر فأكثر عن الخروج إلى العالم،
and more and more, I was sitting in front of my computer screen.
كلما جلست أكثر فأكثر أمام شاشة حاسوبي.
And especially since about 2007, when I got an iPhone,
وبالتحديد منذ سنة 2007، عندما اقتنيت الآيفون،
I was not only sitting in front of my screen all day,
لم أكن فقط أجلس طوال اليوم أمام شاشة الحاسوب،
but I was also getting up at the end of the day
بل كنت أنهض في نهاية اليوم،
and looking at this little screen that I carried in my pocket.
وأنا أنظر إلى إلى تلك الشاشة الصغيرة التي أحمل في جيبي.
And what was surprising to me was how quickly
والذي كان مفاجئا بالنسبة لي هو كيف تغيرت بسرعة
my relationship to the physical world had changed.
علاقتي بالعالم المادي.
In this very short period of time, you know, whether you
في هذه المدة القصيرة، ربما تقدرونها
call it the last 15 years or so of being online, or the last,
بـ15 سنة الأخيرة أو ما شابه من التواجد على الإنترنت، أو لنقل،
you know, four or five years of being online all the time,
أربع أو خمس سنوات من التواجد على الشبكة طوال الوقت،
our relationship to our surroundings had changed in that
فقد تغيرت علاقتنا بمحيطنا حيث أن
our attention is constantly divided. You know,
انتباهنا أصبح مقسما طوال الوقت. تعرفون،
we're both looking inside the screens and we're looking
نحن ننظر من خلال شاشاتنا وكذلك
out in the world around us.
من خلال العالم من حولنا.
And what was even more striking to me, and what I really
والأمر الذي كان أكثر إدهاشا لي، والذي
got hung up on, was that the world inside the screen
تعلقت به أكثر، هو أن ذلك العالم داخل الشاشة
seemed to have no physical reality of its own.
بدى و كأنه لا يملك حقيقة مادية في حد ذاته.
If you went and looked for images of the Internet,
إذا ذهبت و بحثت عن صور على الإنترنت ،
this was all that you found, this famous image by Opte
هذا كل ما كنت تجده، هذه الصورة الشهيرة للأوبت
of the Internet as the kind of Milky Way, this infinite expanse
التي تظهر الانترنت على شكل درب التبانة، ذلك المدى اللامتناهي
where we don't seem to be anywhere on it.
حيث لا نبدو متواجدين في أي من أرجائه.
We can never seem to grasp it in its totality.
وحيث يبدو أننا لا نستطيع إدراكه في مجمله.
It's always reminded me of the Apollo image of the Earth,
دائما ما تذكرني بصورة أبولو للأرض،
the blue marble picture, and it's similarly meant to suggest,
الصورة الرخامية الزرقاء ، التي من المفترض أن تقترح
I think, that we can't really understand it as a whole.
على ما أعتقد، أننا لا نستطيع فهم الأمر بمجمله.
We're always sort of small in the face of its expanse.
إننا بشكل أو بآخر رقعة صغيرة على رقعة فسيحة.
So if there was this world and this screen, and if there was
إذا لو كان لدينا هذا العالم، وهذه الشاشة، وإن كان لدي
the physical world around me, I couldn't ever get them
هذا العالم المادي من حولي، لم أكن لأستطيع قط جمعهم
together in the same place.
معا في مكان واحد.
And then this happened.
بعدها إليكم ما حصل.
My Internet broke one day, as it occasionally does,
في أحد الأيام، انقطع اتصالي بالإنترنت، كما يحصل بين الفينة والأخرى،
and the cable guy came to fix it, and he started with
بعدها جاء عامل الأسلاك لتصليحها، فبدأ
the dusty clump of cables behind the couch,
بكومة الأسلاك المُغبرَّة خلف الأريكة،
and he followed it to the front of my building and into the basement and out to the back yard,
فتعقبها إلى أن وصل إلى أمام بنايتي ثم إلى الطابق الأرضي إلى أن خرج إلى الحديقة الخلفية،
and there was this big jumble of cables against the wall.
وهناك كانت أكوام كبيرة من الأسلاك الملتصقة بالحائط.
And then he saw a squirrel running along the wire,
بعدها رآى سنجابا يجري على السلك،
and he said, "There's your problem.
فقال: "هذه هي مشكلتك.
A squirrel is chewing on your Internet." (Laughter)
سنجاب يمضغ شبكة الإنترنت" (ضحك)
And this seemed astounding. The Internet is
بدا الأمر مذهلا. الإنترنت
a transcendent idea. It's a set of protocols that has changed
هي فكرة رائعة. إنها مجموعة من البروتوكولات التي غيرت
everything from shopping to dating to revolutions.
كل شيء من التسوق إلى المواعدة إلى الثورات.
It was unequivocally not something
إنها بشكل لا ريب فيه ليست شيئا
a squirrel could chew on. (Laughter)
يمكن للسنجاب أن يمضغه. (ضحك)
But that in fact seemed to be the case.
لكن الواقع يؤكد هذا الأمر.
A squirrel had in fact chewed on my Internet. (Laughter)
السنجاب قضم الانترنت الخاص بي.(ضحك)
And then I got this image in my head of what would happen
بعدها حضرت صورة في ذهني عما كان سيحصل
if you yanked the wire from the wall and if you started
لو انتزعت هذا السلك من الحائط وبدأت
to follow it. Where would it go?
تتعقبه. إلى أين كان سيصل؟
Was the Internet actually a place that you could visit?
هل الإنترنت مكان تستطيع زيارته؟
Could I go there? Who would I meet?
هل بإمكاني الذهاب هناك؟ بمن يا ترى سألتقي؟
You know, was there something actually out there?
هل هناك حقا شيء ما يمكن رؤيته؟
And the answer, by all accounts, was no.
والجواب، على جميع الأصعدة، كان لا.
This was the Internet, this black box with a red light on it,
هذه هي الإنترنت، علبة سوداء، عليها ضوء أحمر،
as represented in the sitcom "The IT Crowd."
كما تم تمثيلها في السلسلة الكوميدية " The IT Crowd ".
Normally it lives on the top of Big Ben,
وهي توجد في أعلى ساعة بيغ بن،
because that's where you get the best reception,
لأنك تستطيع من هناك الحصول على أفضل استقبال،
but they had negotiated that their colleague could borrow it
فتفاوضوا على أن تستعيرها منهم إحدى زميلاتهم
for the afternoon to use in an office presentation.
بعد الظهيرة من أجل عرض في المكتب.
The elders of the Internet were willing to part with it
شيوخ الانترنت كانوا يريدون التخلي عنها
for a short while, and she looks at it and she says,
لفترة قصيرة لكن عندما نظرت إليها قالت،
"This is the Internet? The whole Internet? Is it heavy?"
"أهذه هي الإنترنت؟ كل الإنترنت؟ هل هي ثقيلة؟"
They say, "Of course not, the Internet doesn't weigh anything."
قالوا لها: "بالطبع لا، الإنترنت ليس لها وزن."
And I was embarrassed. I was looking for this thing
كنت أحس بالإحراج، لأنني كنت أبحث عن ذلك الشيء الذي
that only fools seem to look for.
يبحث عنه المغفلون فقط.
The Internet was that amorphous blob, or it was a silly
الإنترنت ذلك الشيء الهلامي، أو تلك
black box with a blinking red light on it.
العلبة السوداء السخيفة ذات الضوء الأحمر المومض.
It wasn't a real world out there.
لا يوجد عالم حقيقي هناك.
But, in fact, it is. There is a real world of the Internet out there,
لكن في الواقع، العكس صحيح، هناك عالم حقيقي هناك للإنترنت،
and that's what I spent about two years visiting,
وهذا ما أمضيت حوالي سنتين في زيارته
these places of the Internet. I was in large data centers
في زيارة أمكنة الإنترنت. كنت في مراكز البيانات الضخمة
that use as much power as the cities in which they sit,
التي تستعمل نفس كمية الطاقة التي تحتاجها المدن التي تتواجد بها،
and I visited places like this, 60 Hudson Street in New York,
وقد زرت أمكنة مثل: 60 شارع هادستون في نيويورك،
which is one of the buildings in the world,
الذي يعتبر أحد الأبنية في العالم،
one of a very short list of buildings, about a dozen buildings,
واحد من قائمة قصيرة من البنايات؛ حوالي 12 بناية في العالم،
where more networks of the Internet connect to each other
حيث شبكات الإنترنت متصلة فيما بينها بشكل
than anywhere else.
لا مثيل له في أي مكان آخر .
And that connection is an unequivocally physical process.
وهذا الاتصال هو عملية مادية بحتة.
It's about the router of one network, a Facebook or
يتعلق الأمر بجهاز توجيه لأحد الشبكات، فايسبوك
a Google or a B.T. or a Comcast or a Time Warner, whatever it is,
أو غوغل أو بي تي أو كومكاست أو تايم وارنر أو أيا يكن،
connecting with usually a yellow fiber optic cable up into
متصل في غالب الأحيان بسلك ذي ألياف بصرية صفراء اللون متجه نحو الأعلى
the ceiling and down into the router of another network,
نحو السقف، ونحو الأسفل في اتجاه جهاز توجيه لشبكة أخرى،
and that's unequivocally physical, and it's surprisingly intimate.
كل هذا الأمر يتم بشكل مادي بحت، وبدقة مدهشة.
A building like 60 Hudson, and a dozen or so others,
بناية مثل رقم 60 في شارع هاديسون، ودزينة من البنايات المماثلة،
has 10 times more networks connecting within it
تملك شبكات متصلة فيما بينها أكثر بـ10 أضعاف
than the next tier of buildings.
من القطاع المحادي لها من البنايات.
There's a very short list of these places.
هناك عدد محدود من هذه الأمكنة.
And 60 Hudson in particular is interesting because it's home
والبناء الـ60 في شارع هاديسون بالخصوص مكان مثير للاهتمام لأنه بمثابة البيت
to about a half a dozen very important networks,
الذي يضم نصف دزينة من أهم الشبكات،
which are the networks which serve the undersea cables
وهي الشبكات التي تخدم الأسلاك التي تمر تحت البحر
that travel underneath the ocean
والتي تسافر تحت المحيط
that connect Europe and America and connect all of us.
والتي تربط أوروبا وأمريكا، وتربطنا جميعا.
And it's those cables in particular that I want to focus on.
وهذه الأسلاك بالخصوص هي ما أود التركيز عليه.
If the Internet is a global phenomenon, if we live
إذا كانت الإنترنت ظاهرة عالمية وإذا كنا نعيش
in a global village, it's because there are cables underneath
في قرية عالمية، فلأنه هناك أسلاكا تحت
the ocean, cables like this.
المحيط، أسلاك مثل هذه.
And in this dimension, they are incredibly small.
وبهذا البعد فإنها صغيرة بشكل مذهل.
You can you hold them in your hand. They're like a garden hose.
يمكنك الإمساك بها بيدك، فهي أشبه بخرطوم الحديقة.
But in the other dimension they are incredibly expansive,
لكنها في البعد الآخر، كبيرة جدا
as expansive as you can imagine.
كبيرة أكبر مما تتخيلون.
They stretch across the ocean. They're three or five
تمتد عبر المحيط. ويبلغ طولها ثلاثة أو خمسة
or eight thousand miles in length, and
أو ثمانية آلاف ميل،
if the material science and the computational technology
وإذا كان العلم المادي والتكنولوجيا المعلوماتية
is incredibly complicated, the basic physical process
غاية في التعقيد، فإن العملية الفيزيائية الأساسية
is shockingly simple. Light goes in on one end of the ocean
بسيطة بشكل صادم. يذهب الضوء من نقطة البداية في المحيط
and comes out on the other, and it usually comes
ويصل إلى النقطة الأخرى، وغالبا ما ينطلق
from a building called a landing station that's often
من بناية يطلق عليها محطة هبوط
tucked away inconspicuously in a little seaside neighborhood,
وغالبا ما تكون مدسوسة بعيدا بشكل غير واضح في حي صغير محاد للبحر،
and there are amplifiers that sit on the ocean floor
وهناك مضخمات موجودة في قاع المحيط
that look kind of like bluefin tuna, and every 50 miles
تبدو كسمكة التونة ذات الزعانف الزرقاء، وعلى بعد كل 50 ميل
they amplify the signal, and since the rate of transmission
تضخم الإشارة، وبما أن نسبة الإرسال
is incredibly fast, the basic unit is a 10-gigabit-per-second
سريعة بشكل مذهل، فإن الوحدة الأساسية هي 10 غيغابايت في الثانية
wavelength of light, maybe a thousand times your own
من الطول الموجي للضوء، ما يوازي ربما آلاف أضعاف
connection, or capable of carrying 10,000 video streams,
اتصالكم بالانترنت، أوالقدرة على تحميل 10,000 بث للفيديو ،
but not only that, but you'll put not just one wavelength of light
ليس هذا فحسب، لأنك لن تضع طول موجة واحدة للضوء
through one of the fibers, but you'll put maybe
في واحدة من الألياف، ولكنك ستضع ربما
50 or 60 or 70 different wavelengths or colors of light
50 أو 60 أو 70 أطوال أمواج وألوان مختلفة من الضوء
through a single fiber, and then you'll have maybe
في ليف واحد، وبعدها ستكون لديك ربما
eight fibers in a cable, four going in each direction.
ثمانية ألياف، أربعة منها تتجه في كل الاتجاهات.
And they're tiny. They're the thickness of a hair.
وهي بالغة في الصغر بسمك خصلة شعر.
And then they connect to the continent somewhere.
وبعدها ترتبط بالقارة في مكان ما.
They connect in a manhole like this. Literally,
وترتبط في فتحة كهذه تماما،
this is where the 5,000-mile cable plugs in.
هنا حيث يصل السلك ذو ال5000 ميل.
This is in Halifax, a cable that stretches from Halifax to Ireland.
هنا في هاليفاكس، السلك الذي يمتد من هاليفاكس إلى إيرلاندا.
And the landscape is changing. Three years ago,
والمشهد ماض في التغير منذ ثلاث سنوات،
when I started thinking about this, there was one cable
حين بدأت أبحث في هذا الأمر، كان هناك كابل واحد
down the Western coast of Africa, represented
في اتجاه الساحل الغربي لإفريقيا، ممثل
in this map by Steve Song as that thin black line.
في هذه الخريطة من طرف ستيف سونغ بهذا الخط الأسود الرفيع.
Now there are six cables and more coming, three down each coast.
الآن هناك ستة أسلاك، و المزيد منها قادم، ثلاثة تحت كل ساحل.
Because once a country gets plugged in by one cable,
لأنه حالما تحصل دولة على ربط عبر أحد الأسلاك،
they realize that it's not enough. If they're going to build
يدرك المسؤولون أن هذا غير كاف. إذا كانوا ماضين في
an industry around it, they need to know that their connection
بناء صناعة حولها، عليهم أن يعرفوا
isn't tenuous but permanent, because if a cable breaks,
أن ربطهم ليس هشا بل مستمرا، لأنه لو حصل أن انقطع سلك ما
you have to send a ship out into the water, throw
عليك أن ترسل سفينة إلى البحر، وتلقي
a grappling hook over the side, pick it up, find the other end,
صنارة صيد، تلتقطها، وتجد الطرف الثاني،
and then fuse the two ends back together and then dump it over.
تصهر الطرفين معا مرة أخرى، ثم تغرقهما.
It's an intensely, intensely physical process.
إنها عملية فيزيائية مكثفة.
So this is my friend Simon Cooper, who until very recently
وهذا صديقي سيمون كووبر، الذي كان يعمل حتى وقت قريب
worked for Tata Communications, the communications wing
في طاطا للاتصالات، الجناح المكلف بالاتصالات في
of Tata, the big Indian industrial conglomerate.
طاطا، العملاق الصناعي الهندي.
And I've never met him. We've only communicated
لم ألتقه قط. نتحادث فقط
via this telepresence system, which always makes me
عبر نظام التحادث عن بعد، مما جعلني
think of him as the man inside the Internet. (Laughter)
دائما أراه في صورة الرجل بداخل الإنترنت.(ضحك)
And he is English. The undersea cable industry
وهو بريطاني، و صناعة الأسلاك تحت البحر
is dominated by Englishmen, and they all seem to be 42.
يهيمن عليها البريطانيون، ويبدون جميعا في عمر الـ 42.
(Laughter) Because they all started at the same time
(ضحك)لأنهم بدؤوا جميعا في نفس الوقت
with the boom about 20 years ago.
مع تلك الطفرة التي ظهرت منذ 20 عاما.
And Tata had gotten its start as a communications business
وكانت طاطا قد شقت طريق بدايتها كشركة اتصالات
when they bought two cables, one across the Atlantic
عندما اشترت كابلين، أحدهما يعبر المحيط الأطلسي
and one across the Pacific, and proceeded to add pieces
والآخر يعبر المحيط الهادي، وأضافوا قطعا أخرى
onto them, until they had built a belt around the world,
إليها، حتى بنوا حزاما حول العالم،
which means they will send your bits to the East or the West.
مما يعني أنهم يرسلون بتاتك إلى الشرق أو إلى الغرب.
They have -- this is literally a beam of light around the world,
لديهم حرفيا شعاع من الضوء حول العالم،
and if a cable breaks in the Pacific, it'll send it around
وإذا انقطع كابل في المحيط الهادي، يعيد إرساله
the other direction. And then having done that,
إلى الاتجاه الآخر. وبعد الانتهاء من هذا،
they started to look for places to wire next.
بدؤوا في البحث عن أمكنة جديدة للربط.
They looked for the unwired places, and that's meant
بدؤوا في البحث عن أماكن غير مرتبطة، وهذا يضم
North and South, primarily these cables to Africa.
الشمال والجنوب، بالأساس تلك الكابلات الموجهة إلى أفريقيا.
But what amazes me is Simon's incredible geographic imagination.
لكن ما أدهشني في مخيلة سيمون الجغرافية المدهشة.
He thinks about the world with this incredible expansiveness.
أنه يرى العالم بتلك العين الواسعة.
And I was particularly interested because I wanted to see
كنت مهتما بالأمر لأنني أردت أن أرى
one of these cables being built. See, you know, all the time
عملية بناء أحد هذه الكابلات. تعلمون حين نكون
online we experience these fleeting moments of connection,
متصلين بالإنترنت، نمر بلحظات اتصال سريعة
these sort of brief adjacencies, a tweet or a Facebook post
من قبيل تغريدة على تويتر، أو تعليق على الفايسبوك
or an email, and it seemed like there was a physical corollary to that.
أو بريد إلكتروني، حيث يبدو أن هناك عملية فيزيائية.
It seemed like there was a moment when the continent
يبدو الأمر و كأن قارة بأكملها
was being plugged in, and I wanted to see that.
يتم تشغيلها، فأردت رؤية هذا الأمر.
And Simon was working on a new cable,
وكان سيمون يعمل على كابل جديد.
WACS, the West Africa Cable System, that stretched
WACS، نظام كابل غرب إفريقيا، الذي يمتد
from Lisbon down the west coast of Africa,
من برشلونة إلى الساحل الغربي لأفريقيا،
to Cote d'Ivoire, to Ghana, to Nigeria, to Cameroon.
إلى ساحل العاج ونيجيريا وغانا والكامرون.
And he said there was coming soon, depending
أخبرني أن الأمر سيحصل عما قريب، حسب
on the weather, but he'd let me know when,
أحوال الجو، وأنه سيخبرني متى سيكون ذلك،
and so with about four days notice, he said to go
فأخبرني مسبقا بحوالي 4 أيام، بالذهاب
to this beach south of Lisbon, and a little after 9,
إلى الساحل الجنوبي للشبونة وبعد التاسعة بقليل،
this guy will walk out of the water. (Laughter)
سيخرج هذا الرجل من الماء. (ضحك)
And he'll be carrying a green nylon line, a lightweight line,
سيكون حاملا لخيط نايلون أخضر، خيط خفيف الوزن،
called a messenger line, and that was the first link
يطلق عليه اسم خط المرسال، وكان هذا أول رابط
between sea and land, this link that would then be
بين البحر واليابسة، ويمكنه أن
leveraged into this 9,000-mile path of light.
يحمل مسافة 9000 ميل من الضوء.
Then a bulldozer began to pull the cable in from this
بعدها بدأت جرافة في جر الأسلاك
specialized cable landing ship, and it was floated
من سفينة خاصة بالكابلات، ووضعها
on these buoys until it was in the right place.
في عوامات حتى وصلت للمكان المناسب.
Then you can see the English engineers looking on.
عندها يمكنك أن ترى المهندسين البريطانيين يتفقدونها.
And then, once it was in the right place, he got back
بعدها، حالما تكون الأسلاك في المكان المناسب،
in the water holding a big knife, and he cut each buoy off,
يعود المهندس إلى الماء ومعه سكين كبير فيقطع خيط العوامة،
and the buoy popped up into the air, and the cable
فتطير العوامة في الهواء، وينزل الكابل
dropped to the sea floor, and he did that all the way out
إلى قاع البحر، وقد فعل هذا على طول الطريق
to the ship, and when he got there,
إلى السفينة، وعندما عاد إليها،
they gave him a glass of juice and a cookie,
أعطوه كأسا من العصير وبعض الحلوى،
and then he jumped back in, and he swam back to shore,
ثم قفز ثانية، وسبح إلى أن وصل إلى اليابسة،
and then he lit a cigarette. (Laughter)
وأشعل سيجارة.(ضحك)
And then once that cable was on shore,
حينها، عندما يكون الكابل على الشاطئ،
they began to prepare to connect it to the other side,
يستعد المهندسون لتوصيله إلى الجانب الآخر،
for the cable that had been brought down from the landing station.
هذا بخصوص الكابل الذي تم جلبه من محطة الهبوط.
And first they got it with a hacksaw, and then they start
في البداية يجلبونه مع منشار للمعادن، فيبدؤون
sort of shaving away at this plastic interior with a --
بتقليمه من الداخل البلاستيكي بطريقة
sort of working like chefs, and then finally they're working
أشبه بعمل الطباخين الرئيسيين، وفي النهاية يعملون عليها
like jewelers to get these hair-thin fibers to line up
كصانعي المجوهرات، ليستخلصوا تلك الألياف بحجم خصلة الشعر ولربطها
with the cable that had come down,
بالكابل الذي أُنزل،
and with this hole-punch machine they fuse it together.
فيصهرونها معا بواسطة هاته الآلة الخرامة.
And when you see these guys going at this cable with a hacksaw,
فعندما ترون هؤلاء الأشخاص متوجهين نحو الكابل حاملين آلة منشار المعادن،
you stop thinking about the Internet as a cloud.
تتوقف عن رؤية الإنترنت كسحابة.
It starts to seem like an incredibly physical thing.
إذ تبدو العملية عملية فيزيائية بامتياز.
And what surprised me as well was that as much as this
وماأدهشني أيضا، هو أنه على قدر ما تنبني
is based on the most sophisticated technology, as much
هذه العملية على تكنولوجيا متقدمة جدا، على قدر
as this is an incredibly new thing, the physical process
ما يبدو الأمر جديدا، والعملية الفيزيائية
itself has been around for a long time, and the culture is the same.
نفسها كانت متواجدة منذ زمن بعيد، الثقافة المتبعة هي نفسها.
You see the local laborers. You see the English engineer
يمكن أن ترى عمالا محليين، يمكنك أن ترى مهندسا بريطانيا
giving directions in the background. And more importantly,
يعطي تعليماته في الخلفية، لكن الأمرالأكثر أهمية هنا،
the places are the same. These cables still connect
الأمكنة هي نفسها. هذه الأسلاك تربط
these classic port cities, places like Lisbon, Mombasa,
الموانئ الكلاسيكية للمدن مثل لشبونة ومومباسا
Mumbai, Singapore, New York.
ومومباي وسنغافورة ونيو يورك.
And then the process on shore takes around three or four days,
بعدها يتطلب العمل على الشاطئ حوالي ثلاثة إلى أربعة أيام،
and then, when it's done, they put the manhole cover
وبعدها، حين ينتهي العمل، يضعون عليها غطاء ذي فتحة
back on top, and they push the sand over that,
في الأعلى، ويضعون الرمل على ذلك،
and we all forget about it.
فننسى جميعا الأمر.
And it seems to me that we talk a lot about the cloud,
ويبدو لي أننا نتحدث كثيرا عن الخدمة السحابية،
but every time we put something on the cloud,
ولكن في كل مرة نضع شيئا على السحاب،
we give up some responsibility for it.
نتنازل عن بعض المسؤولية عنها.
We are less connected to it. We let other people worry about it.
أصبحنا أقل ارتباطا بها، وجعلنا الناس قلقين حيالها.
And that doesn't seem right.
وهذا لا يبدو أمرا صحيحا.
There's a great Neal Stephenson line where he says
هناك مقولة عظيمة لنيل ستيفنسون حيث يقول
that wired people should know something about wires.
على الناس المتصلين بالإنترنت أن يتعلموا شيء عن الأسلاك.
And we should know, I think, we should know
وعلينا أن نعرف، باعتقادي، علينا أن نعرف
where our Internet comes from, and we should know
من أين تأتي الإنترنت، علينا أن نعرف
what it is that physically, physically connects us all.
ما هو هذا الأمر المادي الحقيقي الذي يربطنا جميعا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم.(تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thanks. (Applause)
شكرا.(تصفيق)